this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se-radio.net
sc radio is brought to you by the ieee
computer society by ieee software
magazine
online at computer.org software
open zd is the only open source way to
embed zero trust networking into your
app giving you unprecedented control and
security
give your app superpowers using an open
zd sdk and a few lines of code
never face the horrors of vpns dns or
inbound ports
no networking engineering skills needed
openzd is trusted by developers at
microsoft oracle and ramco
if you don't want to host opencd
netfoundry can with free plans at
netfoundry.io
se radio that's n-e-t-f-o-u-n-d-r-y
hello and welcome to software
engineering radio i'm mikhail i'm a
guest host on software engineering radio
and i have the pleasure to introduce pop
to shaw bob is an accomplished writer
software engineer and a data architect
who has been involved involved in the
semantic web since 2002. bob is a an
author who has written books for
o'reilly manning and prentice hall
specifically learning sparkle xslt
quickly and the annotated specification
and html cd for parentasol
he's also wrote it in magazines so he
has written for the modalities magazine
o'reilly
networks xml.com dr top's channel and
even ipm technical works he is currently
a technical writer at katana graph for
makers of a high performance distributed
graph database and is based in
charlottesville virginia and has five
books and nearly 100 online and print
articles about id bob is
proud to never use the word
functionality in any of them bob is
there anything in your bio that i might
have missed or that you would like to
add
i think you've got the key things i mean
i've sort of gone back and forth between
software development solution architect
is always such a vague term but you know
helping customers figure out what
they're going to do and writing it up um
so sometimes more coding sometimes
right now i'm happy to be in a position
where i'm pretty much a full-time writer
awesome so to give listeners a little
bit of an overview on what we are going
to do in this particular
episode we're talking about creating
technical documentation so obviously
there are various types of
documentations and you have a role as a
technical writer right now in katana
craft so perhaps we should start with
a little bit about the technical writer
role itself so the first question would
be why do we need this role why why is a
technical writer necessary for a
software organization
typically i mean to you know people get
a product they want to know how to use
it and there are brilliant programmers
out there who know
you know their favorite favorite
languages inside out and all the cool
things you can do and how to do them
efficiently but those developers might
not know how to explain the end user
usage of those products to people who
are new to it
so explaining to people figuring out
what they're going to want to look up
and how to do these things that's really
the tech writer's job you know to write
the user manual basically user manual or
and reference guide and other things
like that which you know we can talk
about have overlapping responsibilities
but people get a software product they
want to know how to use it so the tech
writer is the person who explains how to
use it
cool so just to dig in a little bit what
are the specialized skills so why why
what does the technical writer bring to
the job that may be a
software engineer with an english
speaking background cannot do
well there's a typically to enjoy
writing i mean because a lot of people
just don't like you know they they view
it as an awful tour you know maybe
someone who writes on the side or has a
blog or something like that but you need
to be able to talk and communicate with
on the one hand end users and on the
other hand with software developers to
understand the the technical parts you
know if you don't if a developer has a
new feature and says here's what it does
and that's not clear of the technical
writer the technical writer has to be
able to ask the right questions to say
you know i get this part of this part
but i you know this part here how does
that work they need to you know sort of
interview them to find out the
information necessary to then explain it
to people who are new to the product who
don't have that technical background so
the communication skills going in two
directions one to the end user and two
to the more technical people the
developers
so does that mean that a technical
writer
needs to have a
software engineering background because
if he's talking to software developers
about technical topics
does that mean that okay
you need to have that same language or
same vocabulary to be able to understand
them
i it helps i do have you know since i
first became a technical writer i along
the way did get a master's in computer
science and that has helped me a lot to
understand the technical talk and also
to help sort out actual technical terms
from buzzwords which is another thing
because you know you hear these words
getting front round some of them have
specific meanings some of them get
misused so i've often joked in some
places that i've worked that having a
master's in computer science helps me to
talk to the phds and then translate what
they're saying to a regular people so it
helps but it's not necessarily
especially if the product is some
products will have end users who are
non-technical you know if it's a phone
app to help you know track something but
some products will have technical end
users um especially if you're going to
be writing about the un api or something
like that so
the ability to
communicate with the developers becomes
more and more important then the more
technical the audience
awesome so
again just to kind of elaborate a little
bit on that so what kind of
documentation technical writers
typically focus
they actually create design or
or architecture documents
more like user facing documentation
like manuals installations is that i
guess a function of what kind of
software project you are writing
documentation for or is this is there
like something that is a standard okay
this is always going to be written by a
technical writer
i would say that you're if someone has a
technical writer role their their
primary job is to write user-facing
documentation this sort of architecture
diagrams and stuff it's it's interesting
to see those and those are good
background when they're developing but
if if a company is going to budget to
have a tech writer that is to have
someone who creates that part of the
product the part of the product that
helps end users get up and running
and there's three basic types of user
documentation and when i first started
this i it was back in the day when there
were printed documentation we would make
three separate volumes for this at the
places where i worked the first would be
a reference guide a reference guide
should explain basically everything
somebody sees in the product you know
every icon every menu choice if they
look at something and think what good is
that what's that for they should be able
to quickly find it and look it up and
see what it does and then apart from the
reference guide the other big one would
be the user guide a user guide is
arranged more in terms of the tasks that
the end user wants to do the the user
guide is really aimed at someone who
doesn't know the product so for example
if it's a database program it would say
how to create a new database how to put
data in there how to edit it you'd
mentioned i wrote a book called xslt
quickly from manning which was about the
xslt
language for manipulating xml i mean i
had come from a background with html
before that xml was basically a simpler
version of sgml and my work with sgml
enabled me to when i wrote the outline
for the xslt book before i even knew how
to write any xslt i was still able to
write a user guide outline because i
knew what the tasks people had to do
work create new elements uh rename
elements convert elements to attributes
and back and forth delete rename i knew
what the basic tasks were so that i
could create an outline that would said
things like how to create elements how
to delete elements how to rename
attributes to and so forth so when
someone's looking at a user guide they
want to see the the names of the tasks
the the user guide shouldn't be talking
about the
talking in the technical language or at
least the table of contents should not
be talking in the technical language of
the product it should be talking in
terms of the tasks that users want to
get done and and that's not always easy
because you have to maybe work with
marketing or work with some of the ui
developers to find out to understand the
users you know what are they trying to
do with this product what are the
various things how do those things fit
together you really need to get inside
the user's head so you can then explain
here's how to do this here's how to do
this and that brings me to the third
category of documentation along with
reference guide and user guides would be
i might call it a quick start or getting
started but a tutorial sometimes i've
seen getting started to cover
installation as well but a tutorial for
someone who's never used the product
which i consider almost like a demo like
giving a demo to yourself you know step
one click here step two click here and
this comes up that's you know for this
great reason because to sort of show off
the cool parts of the product maybe even
in this in a way similar to what a
someone giving a demo and from a
conference might do to go through 10 or
15 steps to show the cool parts of the
product a tutorial i think is something
where a script your someone can give
that demo to themselves and see how cool
the product is and how to do the basic
things
so those i guess would be the three
categories reference guide user guide
and a quick start tutorial so as a
software developer if i am interested in
this field so how do what what are the
kind of
things skills i need to cultivate maybe
there are there's some simple guidelines
that as developers we can follow to
improve
our documentation for maybe our site
project or maybe even if it's our
project and then
and we've been asked to do some
documentation what are some simple
guidelines or things that we can do to
make sure that we're kind of writing
good technical documentation
and here's something i'm probably going
to say a lot that there are a lot of
analogies to writing the software itself
so for example with documentation
if the software was developed from a
well-organized set of requirements those
requirements are going to be very useful
to you you know there's this list saying
customers should be able to do this
customer should be able to do this so if
you have some well-written requirements
that's a great place to start here's how
to do this here's how to do this
other things include
i always like to think of two classes of
reviewers when you write explaining
something you want to show it to
of course a developer someone to make
sure that you explained it correctly
that you know you didn't get anything
wrong but you also want to
what i call a target audience reviewer
someone who
doesn't know the product has some
interest in learning the product have
them read what you wrote and see
could they follow along you know
did your explanation work for them and
and if not where so those two kinds of
reviewers i think are important to keep
in mind um when you're developing
something
okay
so are there any simple things that we
can do in terms of the language itself
so maybe
like so
maybe so yeah this is a good way of
putting so how
is grammatical accuracy
absolutely
vital or is it okay to say okay
as long as i'm technically accurate
some grammatical
errors are fine uh it's not that
strong or requirement
what do you think well
i mean grammar it's you know it's not
like you know when you're writing code
and if you forgot a semicolon the whole
thing's not going to compile right it'll
still be there but
if the grammar is bad it's probably
going to be harder to understand you
know if if you're if you have a plural
subject with a singular verb
people reading it are going to you know
stop and go back and it's going to be
harder to follow so i think grammatical
accuracy
you know simple things like that and
punctuation
these things i think are important if
it's going to be harder for the
technical parts to be put across if it's
done with mistakes in the grammar um now
i know another you know when we were in
secondary school and we wrote these
papers and handed them in and our
teachers gave them back with lots of red
markings saying you know you used the
passive voice here you should have used
the active voice um there are reasons
for these things and like the famous
drunken white book element of style it
makes
your
writing easier to read um to do things
like that it's to to imitate good
writers i mean to to vary the structure
of your sentences i mean when you when
you're reading someone who's who's
reading you like
sometimes it's it's nice to stop and
step by and think well why do i like
this person's writing you know look at
the structure of the sentences and do
they mix up long ones and short ones and
things like that if it's easier to read
people are going to have more motivation
to read it and you want people to read
it
but another point i was going to bring
up a big difference from technical
writing from other typical prose writing
is that
people aren't going to read
what you wrote from beginning to end you
know it's not a novel they picked up
that documentation because they want to
look something up they want to see how
to do something and so
that's with technical writing
we typically encourage more use make it
easier to skim by doing things like
bulleted lists numbered lists tables if
it's just gray paragraphs on a white
page it's a lot harder to find i mean
you could put a lot of sub heads in i
guess
and with online documentation too it's
easier to search which was not the case
with hard copy paper
i will throw in before i forget about
with lists bulleted lists versus
numbered lists i've seen
people will often use
numbered lists when they should have
used a bulleted list if i say um right
there are three things to remember when
you're going to do this one boom two
boom three boom well are those three
things is that order
really essential for that you know of
course it's essential when you're
writing an installation guide you know
do this set these environment variables
run this script download this you know
of course those steps certainly deserve
to be a numbered list but if i say you
know there are three things to remember
i find that people often
are very quick to make something a
numbered list when it doesn't really
need to be one they should be a bullet
list so things like that
bullet lists
nested bullet list listed numbered list
these things are how we break down the
information that we're presenting so
that people can skim and find the
answers to the questions they have about
how to do things with your product
that's very interesting and i find it
interesting that you mentioned that you
know
large blobs of gray text on a page don't
kind of invite the user to read it so
as i think of that what do you think
about you know some of the newer ways
i've seen documentation
kind of get created right so nowadays
it's not just
text it's also video it is
images
there's a lot of rich media that can be
leveraged so
what do you think in general of that
trend do you think it's something that's
can be considered technical writing in
what is the importance of a good
document do you need to have you know
the same kind of consideration when
you're creating your tutorial video as
you do when you create an faq or a
tutorial document
sure i think
you know when we say technical writer i
remember that there was an organization
i think i may have been a member years
ago called the society of technical
communicators stc
people who
think about these other media as well i
think when you get into other media
besides text
again like with software you're creating
something
you have to think about how maintainable
is this thing i'm creating you know six
months from now
if the product changes and this is
obsolete do i have to redo the whole
thing can i go in and fix one little bit
i mean if you wrote a series of bulleted
numbered lists and you need to add one
list item to one of the lists in the
text that's easy enough if you spent
seven hours making a half hour video and
some of the things halfway through it
are no longer apply
then that's a bigger deal i mean even
with screenshots even with images
sometimes
you know i was working somewhere once
where they just changed the logo of the
product that was in the upper left so
everything still worked the same but now
all these screenshots you know they
looked out of date and you know there
are ways to deal with it but thinking
ahead about maintainability like that
is important in getting back to videos
you know imagine a 20-minute video that
explains how to do 10 things
and now
the fourth thing is done differently um
so you're gonna remake the whole video
or
you know that that can be a real pain so
one approach is to have a series of two
minute videos that explain how to do a
specific thing
that's not always as easy as it sounds
because some of these things might be
building on each other and also managing
a bunch of two minute videos and their
relationships and making it clear to the
audience which one goes with which
there's there's the maintenance is more
difficult i think videos are especially
useful for
you know if it's a graphical user
interface and for demos you know we
click here and then here and then this
pops up and look there's our data and
look look you know it got processed and
now it we can see the results of the
query or the analysis
i think that's very useful to show how
something's done
although another thing about creating
videos is that people can be
you know audio quality sometimes people
think well my coworkers can hear me with
this headset i'm wearing on a zoom call
so my audio quality is fine whereas i
mean nikhil you you and i we had a
separate meeting before our discussion
today just to talk about
mics and the rooms we'd be in and
recording so
podcasters
of course care
more about think harder about
having good audio quality sometimes when
people make videos to demo software
they'll just use the same mic and so
forth they do in the meeting and don't
realize that that can really diminish
the product so just going out and buying
a 20 mic or something like that can help
i mean i guess i'm kind of rambling here
but i would like to mention besides
different kinds of technologies for
creating documentation along with
video and images and audio another one
that's i think being used more and more
these days especially
especially with products that involve
code are notebooks like jupiter
notebooks zeppelin notebooks those are
great because they let you format things
have your bulleted and numbered lists
and all that and mix them with code that
people can then see execute themselves
or you know i put in a sample someone
reading it can modify the sample and see
that so i think that's been a pretty
exciting development in documentation of
code um that it doesn't help so much
with graphical user interfaces
so that was that was kind of rambling i
hope i addressed if there's anything i
missed let me know
hey no i think you did quite well so
obviously we have touched upon some of
the
challenges of maintaining video versus
text and that i think
is is also kind of brings out an
underlying point which is that
software products are not snapshots that
never change right software products
evolve over time
documentation needs to be updated
and the more documentation you have of
varying levels of
depth
there's always something that needs to
be changed right so even if it is a
minor version upgrade maybe there's an
api change or that is that that needs
the reference manual to be updated for
example
so obviously this has consequences
so as people may use documents that are
no longer correct and get frustrated so
from a user perspective definitely out
of date documentation is a problem
but how do you actually see how
do we
do we have a solution from a process
perspective or a tooling perspective how
do you actually
work with
how to evolve documentation along with
software let's say
well two things here one i guess would
be the creation maintenance and another
would be distribution for creation and
maintenance it's more and more
basically you you check it into the
version control system you know here's
the new features for release 4.2 here's
the write-up of release 4.2 and that way
they can they can stay in sync
for distribution
what i've seen a lot of companies do i
mean katanagraph does as well
is when they're publishing the
documentation because most documentation
these days it's going to be html right
you're going to have basically a website
showing the books and the sub sections
and you can navigate through there so
you might have the html would often
include or rather the urls would often
include the release number right in it
so it's like your companyname.com
documentation slash 4.2 slash index.html
and then slash 4.3 and you can leave
them all up there and then what a lot of
companies will do is they'll have your
companyname.com documentation
latest
which is set to redirect to the most
recent one so that way you're leaving
all the documentation up for multiple
releases at the same time as a
distribution thing but there's still a
single url the latest one so that people
can see
what is the current state of the
documentation and what is what is the
documentation for the current state of
the product
so
just just to kind of also think about
outlook of some of the alternatives over
there so you mentioned versioning
systems so do you think is that kind of
like versioning systems the way we think
about software versioning systems like
maybe
get your subversion do you think that
versioning there are tools like google
docs that have versions in it or even
dropbox for example does does things
like basic versioning of documents now
do you do you think that's that's which
do you think is a way that you prefer
maintaining uh documentation
and also keep in mind that okay
like we had discussed earlier some of
that documentation might be binary so we
don't really
have a way of
keeping
portions of the
document right you if it's like an image
you'll always and that you've updated
your image you're going to have
like the entire image again right you'll
have a new copy of the image or a new
version of the image so what do you
think is suitable is it is it fine to
use google docs or do you think that
technical writers need to use the same
tooling that developers do
they need to use the same tool as
developers
but i mean the fact that the versioning
can sync right in with the software
itself because a lot of documentation
now i mean i could discuss this more
later but people are creating files
you're writing files
that are then going to be part of a
build for documentation so that you know
like this html based distribution i
mentioned if a designer at the company
decides oh i don't like this font or we
need a bigger margin here they're going
to change some css and like with any
website then regenerate everything so
that generation
is part of it's it's a built just like
with software in fact some companies
it's part of the same build as building
the software
so
working with that system of the build
the the use of the um you know checking
in the tools and tagging and get and you
know you you can really take advantage
of all the same things you can do with
code to do that with something like
google docs i mean i think it's great
for internal documentation but i always
thought the worst case with
documentation some little companies will
do is they create a word file right
here's a five-page word file about how
to use the product and then when a new
release comes they'll pull up their word
file and revise some of it and
and you know
they'll give they'll put i hate when
they put the word final in the uh file
name you know maybe generate a pdf from
that or maybe even give people the word
file which is a pretty amateurish way to
do it and google docs is great for so
many things but
the versioning of it and tying that to
release versions of the software you're
much better off using you know the tools
that a software company already has in
place to do that to do you know git or
bitbucket or whatever to keep track of
the pieces and the relationship of the
pieces and the relationship of those
pieces to the releases
so it's you know sometimes for a tech
writer to learn the arcana of git can be
frustrating but
you know it's not like you're doing a
lot of rebasing and so forth with with
documentation so you don't have to get
that far into the difficult get weeds
i'm in my experience so far
yeah yeah that's a great point and just
you mentioned also earlier about
uh publishing the document as a html
website so one of the things i've
noticed especially in in the open source
world
is the rise of you know these specific
things like read the talks or specific
kind of website software as a service
platforms right where get books read the
docs etc where you can actually
they actually handle the
hosting and publication and they even
have you know things like searching your
documentation for various work across
various versions etc so
from that perspective
do you
have a
process or a tool chain for building
documentation from the point of okay
i've
now entered the content so i know this
this is the this is the content that i
would like to
publish and then kind of like is that
like a
a good tool chain that you've used or
maybe you can talk a little bit about
your
your experience with older tools and
stuff like that but
typically what is the tool chain that
one typically uses nowadays to generate
these websites and the css and html and
all that
i think some of the most popular tools
now are basically
tools for generation of static websites
that are
often specialized for documentation so
for example where i am now in my last
position that i held before we used
sphinx with sphinx you're creating the
actual content in restructure text it's
one of those
markdown descendants
so you know asterisk on either side to
bold or italics and so forth but then
you can still have your css and have the
structure to show that
these
six pages here
i want to create a table of contents
here that has those six in this order
and that all gets automated the
generation of all that html and when you
have these files like this the rst and
the css and
other things like that it makes it
easier to
incorporate into a version controls into
you know git or something like that then
it would be if you were like revising
word files over and over so it can be
part of the software documentation tool
chain and then they'll have a build
process and some places will
integrate it more deeply or not into the
software build process but as part of a
release you know you want to make sure
you're getting the three-point stop 3.2
stuff 3.2 product and 3.2 code all in
the same place so it often is tightly
integrated there so i have found that
very useful and it's
also because of its relation to markdown
it's easier for developers are used to
that so they don't mind writing in that
if i could back off and go into a little
history
back in the
i guess in the 1980s
there were when computerized type
setting was becoming a big thing these
companies would
say yeah you can deliver you know files
with codes of how you want your books
laid out and where you want the fonts
and all that and those things that could
have been delivered on you know tape for
all i know
so you put in these codes would you want
a head these codes when you want a sub
head and these codes for bullets and so
forth but different competing companies
doing that they had their own sets of
codes
and some people i think some at ibm in
particular i know for sure but some
other places as well they said wait a
minute we don't want to
tie up all of our have all of our
documentation written using your
proprietary codes we want to have more
flexibility
so they came up with a
what became an iso standard um sgml a
way to define a structure of a document
and then to use that structure
definition to say you know let's say
you're gonna have a cookbook i wanna
create something it's gonna be
one or more recipes and a recipe is a
title and then it's a list of
ingredients and a list of steps and then
there's going to be a part how many it
serves so they would with sgml you could
define a structure like this and then
create the documents in this case
recipes and then automate the checking
of does the structure confine to
does it follow the structure that i
defined and if if you know that it
follows a structure you can automate a
lot more you can then turn this is in
the early days of you know multimedia
getting beyond paper i'm going to turn
it into online help i'm going to turn it
to cd-rom so i'm going to turn it into
html
and so i was got involved in html and i
would go to the conferences and i got to
know some of the people
who did it and some of them
realized html and it's soft some of the
software is very expensive for doing
this um some of the sgml was very
complicated so some of these people got
together and thought we need to create a
simpler easier version of sgml something
that wouldn't take so much computing
power something that could be parsed
with
a program that's you can just download
over the internet with this new language
sun microsystems has called java so that
was
90s i guess so they were working on the
simplified version of sgml they first
the first original working title for it
was web sgml
not as catchy and then someone thought
of a catchy name xml and that's where
xml comes from it was a simplified
version of sgml so a lot of the tool
chains
sgml when it was invented for this
that's what places like boeing
and large defense contractors to
document you know the engine parts they
were thinking back then that
documentation we should treat it like
software in terms of
breaking it down into components if this
subsystem of this engine is also used on
other engines as well we should be able
to write up how to clean how to repair
this subsystem and then take that right
up and add it to the documentation for
the other engines as well
so those were some of the early
moves toward making documentation
componentized just like software so that
it could be mixed and matched and used
for different products and there would
be the tool chains for sgml and later
xml to do you know what what i was
saying about sphynx now that you would
have
your css here you'd have tools for
i'm generating the html from there or
the online help or the cd-rom um
developers didn't like dealing directly
with the xml as much markdown's a little
simpler and there were tools to be a
little more gooey-ish a little look a
little more like word that would still
output the appropriate xml
but sometimes those could be expensive
so that's another
sort of
lineage of the the tool chain for
creating software documentation hardware
documentation is xml and related tools
people don't realize that that's what
xml was for because when it was xml was
first invented it was around the time
the dot-com boom
and with the dot-com boom
early 2000s there were people you know
we're gonna have seamless e-commerce and
have this computer communicate with that
other one across the web to send the
orders and and respond to the orders but
sending and responding to these orders
they had to send these batches of of
data that didn't necessarily fit into
csv they would have more complicated
structures than that so they saw this
xml thing from the w3c
we can define our own structures you
know here's the beginning of a order
here's the end here's an address here's
the the list of items being ordered and
so forth so they started using xml for
that to do this e-commerce basically the
kind of things people are using json for
now they started using it and thought
this is perfect and then they decided no
this isn't perfect at all the data
typing system is weird and whoever
designed it did a terrible job well they
didn't realize that whoever designed xml
was not designing it for the uses they
were putting it for for i'm handing
arbitrary
handfuls of data about transactions back
and forth
time scale db from your friends at time
scale is the leading open source
relational database with support for
time series data
time series data is time stamped so you
can measure how a system is changing
time series data is relentless and
requires a database like time scale db
with speed and petabyte scale
timescale db is the
you know and love with time series super
powers
familiarity flexibility speed that's
time scale
visit them today at tsdb.co
se radio that's tsdb.co
se radio
just to quickly just jump in over there
so when i remember that we went down
this whole pack with xml about you know
the web standard ws star and the whole
set of web servers xml standards
i think one of the
maybe the
things that kind of led to the adoption
of json and other standards like that
was the fact that
you had
all of this ceremony around
how what a document should be like
but i also remember at that time there
was this competing specifically for
documentation there was this other thing
called rdf right
and
i was just wondering you know is that
was that actually
something that could have if
appropriately championed been something
that kind of
took over the documentation side of
things that xml kind of was meant to
have or meant to be for
no rdf is great at metadata documents
but but to have a series of paragraphs
with
sentences where there's inline thing you
know in the middle of a sentence i have
a link i have a bolded term rdf is not
good for that our rdf is about reducing
data down to these these three part
statements called triples so i can say
employee 38 has a higher date of january
1st employee 38 has a last name of smith
and then the flexibility it give that
rdf gives you over something like a
relational database enables lots of new
things including the ability to
aggregate data from different sources
and things like that and i mean i could
go on and on about rdf but
for linear
yeah so it was more or more for
more it was more of uh something that
that external is trying to aim to be
like what the web services was trying to
be that was
perhaps a better better way of doing it
you know for something like json you're
better off i think with rdf the metadata
when you have especially a lot of you
know in the field of digital humanities
and a lot of publishers they have
content from lots of different places
and they want to keep track of the
content and that content and those
different things will have different
bits of metadata but sometimes they're
related even though they're different
because from this standards body or that
one and so mapping between the standards
so that they can then query across all
their metadata for a range of things
rdf's really good for that but not for
the content itself the sort of narrative
content of paragraphs and bulleted and
numbered lists
we could do a whole test on rdf
yeah yeah so to come back a little bit
on
back to our
technical documentation topic
one of the things that i've
seen you mentioned
using things and the
the tool chains like that and
we also discussed some of the older
tools like html and xml but it seemed to
me sometimes that depending on the type
of documentation
some of this is
more automatable and others are less
right so for example
we talked about earlier in
what kind of technical documentation
should be generated we talked about faqs
tutorials high level
technical
technical documents
which explain things to non-technical
people
but at the same time if you have
something like a json api or http api
we also have thing uh tools like swagger
which
you can just point out the
the specification of the api itself in
some cases it kind of generates the
[Music]
documentation out of it right it's
almost like you can it will
look at the types of the
various
response and requests and and that kind
of create a document that allows you to
in some cases even create sample
example requests and responses that you
can
use for testing
but i sometimes get the feeling that
okay
that is again too low level where do you
see the balance between the two should
be right how much of
the documentation that you generate for
a software project can be generated like
that and how much of it is still
something that you want to make sure
that you write in a proper manner
that's a good question i think like i
mentioned
something like a tutorial you really
want to think carefully about the order
you're going to explain things and what
you have the person do
of the three buckets i mentioned of
tutorials reference guides and user
guides with reference guides it can be a
little more automated um like with
swagger i've used it i can't remember
the name
is that was that the tool you mentioned
that can pull things out of apis and
generator
yeah yeah so swagger is basically a part
of the open api i think it's called the
json api documentation tooling and what
it does is it kind of looks at json's
documents and kind of generates
the request
it generates about web-based
documentation which has
which details on all the
lists are all the attributes
properties and then the types of it
which is right and i believe it it will
pull out
yeah and pull out some of the
comments as well from the from the
function so you can get a high level
two-line description of what what the
api does but then that depends on how
well you've commented it
exactly and and that's you know garbage
in garbage out i mean that's
you of a tool that can go through and
pull out and see oh
this function takes three parameters and
the parameters are supposed to be of
these types and it returns something of
this type you know that's nice
to automate the pulling of all that and
the enumeration of it but this the doc
strings how often have we seen doc
strings that just didn't explain what we
wanted explained
so
and that can be a tech writer function
too to
review that documentation and then maybe
create some tickets and say hey you go
back and you know revise that doc string
to explain that
that um better and one of my pet peeves
is whether it's explaining the fields on
a
dialog box or parameter being passed to
a function if we say
here's a parameter called foo and the
documentation says enter the fu value
there
and i'm thinking okay but what is foo
you know what role does food play in
this application and what kind of things
you know might i put there so the
explanation that goes in there you know
tools like that they're like make tools
you know it's great how they can pull
everything together and then create the
thing you're looking for but but the
things they're pulling together have to
have some quality and sometimes they can
help point to you know which parts need
to be updated but still it's it's
garbage and garbage out
right
so
earlier we mentioned and you talked
about
uh keeping and using the same
kit tooling and the version tooling and
trying to keep the documentation
versions the same as the software so as
every new version of software you also
bought the version of documentation and
kind of
maintaining that so
if basically we make if we kind of from
a process perspective say
the
software as a software engineer we
basically approach dot strings or
comments and we kind of write
a proper explanation for every function
and
basically try to
use that as documentation
do you think that theoretically it while
theoretically it is possible to kind of
mix that in
do you still feel that there is a
separate place required or a separate
folder or maybe a separate project
within your git version repository where
you should keep
a separate
viewpoint or a separate perspective or a
separate type of documentation
this really gets back i think to the
distinction between reference guides and
user guides reference guide that this is
all reference guide stuff you know you
want to list everything i mean i think
when someone looks at a product and they
see
some strange icon or menu choice and
think well what's that for the reference
guide is where they would look it up to
find it out in fact
with a graphical user interface
and this can be difficult but i think
it's important
every tool tip
should be
you know if there's some strange icon
you don't know what it means but you
mouse over it and you see some tool tip
that tool tip that should be something
that the user can search on the
reference guide and and i've worked
places where i had to tell the customer
developers before each new release which
tool tips got changed i want to be able
to name all the tool tips in the
documentation because that's the hook
for people to find out what the icon is
for
so a lot of the reference guides for not
only for technical things like apis but
even for the gui because for the
graphical user interface to explain
everything they see they should be able
to look up what that is
on the other hand
a point i wanted to bring up about user
guides is that well i mentioned how when
i wrote a table of contents for an xslt
book i didn't use any xslt terms i
talked about the tasks to do
if let's say for example your product
has a component to develop a schema and
it's called schema wiz okay
and you're going to document that now
to me
if the user guide has a header called
getting started with schema whiz that's
not a very good title i mean i want to
see titles like
creating a new schema revising an old
schema deleting schemas you know naming
the tasks that need to be done as
opposed to
using you know the the terms you made up
for your product as part of the driver
of the user guide so i guess to get back
to your your question about a place for
something separate from the
the lists of things that's where the
user guides go to something organized by
the tasks they want to do as opposed to
something that or that is organized by
the product itself being organized by
the product itself is still important
because that's when they see something
in the product that you know that's
where they go the reference guide to see
what is this thing for what good would
this do for me so i guess to simplify to
getting back to your original question
that is the distinction to me between
reference guides and user guides
right
so again with uh
nowadays basically there is this
idea of an x as code philosophy right so
you have dev devsec ops
documentation so so we have security as
code configuration as code
x something else
this is philosophy that everything kind
of starts becoming encoded and we kind
of been discussing how
close documentation is and how strongly
coupled they are with code so should we
be treating
approaching our documentation as code
and kind of
completely
have not just
the version control
have software processes for it so we can
have like full requests for our
documentation
the icd for our documentation
we have like a merge review process we
have like we have code reviews we have
documentation reviews what do you think
about this particular what is your
opinion on this
i mean i agree with it i i think that
treating it as code lets you take
advantage of all these tools that you
have that you already have to to work
with your code so for example with code
with reviews review of documentation
like code reviews you know a lot of
companies i write something i need it
reviewed i create a jira ticket and you
know to assign someone to review it and
then we say this this feature is held up
until someone does the review just like
when someone's reviewing you know some c
code that was written so i think that
treating it as code has the advantage of
letting you take advantage of all these
tools which is why the old-fashioned way
of creating a word file to have the
documentation there you know doesn't let
you take advantage of these these tools
and things so
using the tool set is the advantage you
get from treating it as code so i think
that's been encouraged in a lot of
places right down to the use of jira
tickets to assign documentation tasks
okay so how then in if
given that right that's in smaller
companies
it is also
often
the role of whoever's doing the software
documentation to also develop uh things
for marketing right so and for sales so
they'll have like in in a in a startup
you might have the same
technical writer or even software
developer for example being approached
by the marketing department and saying
hey okay
we would like you to write a write up
something about this particular feature
that we can blog about or post about or
share with uh in our email newsletter
for example
do you think the skills required
for this kind of
writing right so writing marketing
content and writing sales content
how similar is that or how different is
it from
writing technical documentation i think
it's very similar because you know
especially
when you're writing technical
documentation things like
tutorials as i mentioned and even
release notes i i consider to
essentially be marketing documents
because with both the tutorial and
release notes what you're seeing is look
at this cool stuff isn't this great you
know here here's this thing for you to
use so i think of them as as marketing
documentation
marketing communications is is a way to
sell things to say
what are the great things about the
product and why people should be
interested in using it in a
within an organization you're sometimes
working with the marketing people
you become the tech editor they might
start throwing you know the things that
make your product cool may be associated
with buzzwords that they like to throw
around but don't fully understand that's
pretty common so
making that technical documentation more
making the marketing communications more
technically accurate i think is a big
part of that and and they're usually
happy to have you right
or and a couple places i've worked where
they'll have a developer a software
developer write a blog entry and then
you as the tech writer
rearrange it a bit to make it more
user-friendly not only to customers but
to potential customers i mean people who
just came across your blog and or even
more on technical but thinking of maybe
buying the product so that the technical
writer is sort of coordinating between
developers and marketing people to help
create new blog entries
so
what do you think that we should also
include this category into our idea of
documentation as code and kind of
subject it to the same kind of processes
do you think that that still works or is
that something
that is
difficult to do when you start involving
third parties like sales and marketing
and all those people who may not be
familiar with it
yeah probably not the same processes
because you know sales and marketing
people
it's you know assigning them tickets and
having them check things in to get is it
might be
a bit too much to ask for but i think
helping them to coordinate the the
content itself to to make sure that it
is technically accurate but well written
that all
is um i think very useful and they're
probably gonna have their own tools you
know they might be creating powerpoint
presentations and they want your help
with that or word files that they are
going to turn into pdfs so they're going
to have their own processes and and the
developer processes of using git and so
forth is probably going to be over their
heads but you know you're the liaison
between them between the marketing
people and developers it's it's your job
as a tech writer to translate the
technical stuff to the non-technical
people so that is an interesting place
to help apply that to helping with the
marketing
awesome
[Music]
bob i think we've kind of reached the
end of what i had in mind
in our conversation so far we talked
about
software documentation
from the perspective of uh reference
manuals and user manuals and guides and
things like that
there's also especially if you're
writing
if you're part of a software project
that's a pretty substantial software
software product
you might be asked well
can we create a book okay and can we
create some kind of substantial
artifact out of it right so maybe we
publish a book a book about the project
is that
the same as or similar to
in terms of process
to creating technical documentation
do you think a book book is a good way
of
writing about a software product that
keeps changing and keeps evolving just a
couple of questions
well you could i mean
the user guide material you have you
know that that could be an output format
there are ways to just turn that into a
hard copy book but i think a related
issue about a book is that some people
will see
okay o'reilly has a bunch of books about
oracle products you know that would be
cool if there was an o'reilly book about
our product or or manning or one of the
big you know computer publishers some
and i work places where people thought
oh wouldn't that be cool
and
writing a separate book to go with the
publisher i mean some publishers will
work with you to do a short book that
you can then give away but you know
that's going to cost you money but to
write a complete book about something
that is a sort of separate entity from a
separate publisher
it's fun when it's done but it's a lot
more work than people realize and
you know we were talking earlier about
one of the issues of making videos is
you put a huge amount of work into
something that could be obsolete six
months later if you're going to put five
or six hundred hours into writing a book
that is going to be that could
potentially be obsolete a year later a
year and a half later
and that's an important thing to think
about the resources that go into the
creation of the book and when i've
written books they've usually been about
standards because standards move more
slowly in their upgrades than products
from companies um so if you're writing
about release 3.2 of something you know
when 3.5 is out people aren't going to
look too hard at your book and it can be
a lot more
you know some people
they'll think like well it takes me
half an hour to write a page so a 300
page book that would take me 150 hours
and and that's not how it works you know
one of the reasons you could write that
page in half an hour is because you
already had that page's worth of content
in your head all organized there's a lot
more work to do to organize the content
for 300 pages
secondly even if you could write 300
pages in 150 hours that's just your
first draft it's got to go through
additional drafts just to improve the
writing to make sure it's technically
correct plus you're going to have a lot
of research to do some people think oh
well we could do it half the time if two
people wrote it together but it's uh
it's gonna be more like 70 percent of
the time because you have to coordinate
what you're doing and then once the
thing gets upgraded you know your book
is going to look um out of date so
there are some highlights to writing a
book about your software to be published
by
you know a publisher that i was going to
say puts things in bookstores we don't
see that so much but puts things on
amazon where people can buy the book but
it can be a lot more work
and you have to consider how quickly it
will become obsolete you know once you
have an upgrade or two it's all this
work you did is already history does
that address what you're asking i was
kind of rambling there
i think that's a great overview of of
some of the challenges of book writing
and i'm sure
the not the least of it is also the
different
process that the book publishers might
have right it might not be the same
thing that you're used to following with
your technical articles with you'd
probably have editorial oversight as
well but yeah i mean i think that's
that's a great point to
kind of end this podcast i just wanted
to ask bob if our listeners would like
to
follow or contact you
is there or maybe you'd like to talk
about some of the things that you're
working on right now and then do you do
you want to this is your chance
if people want to contact me on twitter
i'm bob dc bob dc and also i did manage
to get many years ago the domain name
bobdc.com so you can find out more about
the books i've written and that's also
where i have my blog so there are
several
i can send you a link nikhil to put in
the show notes of a series of blog posts
i did several years ago really about
writing documentation about some of
these issues we've covered and some
other things to keep in mind
awesome we will definitely add that to
the show notes
and i guess that all that means
thanks thank you bob this has been a
pretty engaging conversation i think it
will be very valuable to our listeners
thank you for spending the time with us
well thank you for having me it's it's
going to be out driving around my car
listening to a podcast where i'm the one
talking so i'm sure you're used to that
by now
but it's been a lot of fun and i love
talking about this stuff thank you bob
thanks for listening to sc radio an
educational program brought to you by
ieee software magazine for more about
the podcast including other episodes
visit our website at se radio.net
to provide feedback you can comment on
each episode on the website or reach us
on linkedin facebook twitter or through
our slack channel at scradio.slack.com
you can also email us at team
sc-radio.net
this and all other episodes of sc radio
is licensed under creative commons
license 2.5
thanks for listening